This is what Paul Kagame said during his speech at the 30th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide
in Kigali on Sunday. It was the international community which failed all of us whether from
contempt or cowardice. And then this tweet by the Israeli president who attended the
commemorations started making rounds on social media, with people wondering why Isaac Erzog,
whose state is currently enacting a devastating military campaign on Palestinians in Gaza
and committing plausible genocide according to the International Court of Justice,
was invited in the first place. Well see, Africa's relations with Israel vary from country to country,
and although the African Union's attitude towards Israel has toughened in the last six months,
not all African leaders have followed the institution's stance. That includes Paul Kagame.
And this despite serious accusations that have been made about Israel's involvement
in supporting the Rwandan genocide in the first place. As President Erzog noted in his tweet,
the Rwandan people and the Jewish people are connected as they both have suffered a gruesome
genocide. But his tweet overlooks serious allegations about Israel selling weapons to the majority Hutu
that committed massacres against the Tutsis in 1994. In 2014, Israeli activist and lawyer
Ete Mac asked his country's defense ministry for details about the weapons and equipment that
Israel sold to Rwanda. Some of the weapons reportedly used included Israeli-made bullets,
grenades, and rifles. Ete Mac had submitted several Freedom of Information Act requests over the years
to uncover information about Israel's arms sales to countries involved in genocides at the time of
the transactions, such as Bosnia, Chile, Uganda, and Guatemala, and of course, Rwanda. But a court in
Tel Aviv rejected his request. Finally, in 2016, the Israeli Supreme Court ruled that records
documenting Israel's arms sales to Rwanda during the 1994 genocide would remain sealed and concealed
from the public, citing pressing security and foreign relations concerns. Well, rest assured that
the diplomatic relations between the two countries went on to blossom. Three years after that, in 2019,
Israel opened an embassy in Rwanda. The two countries have also vowed to cooperate in various fields,
with Israel pledging support to Rwanda in health, education, agriculture, and cybersecurity. And a
year prior, in 2018, after a visit to Kenya, where he also met with Paul Kagame, Israeli Prime Minister
Benjamin Netanyahu announced that Israel would begin forcibly deporting migrants to third countries,
which have been widely reported to be Uganda and Rwanda. Following a demonstration by a thousand
Eritrean asylum seekers outside the Rwandan embassy in Israel, the Rwandan government went on to deny
that they had a secret deal with Israel. Now, fast forward to April 7th, and the Israeli president
visited Kigali as a guest of honor at the Qubuka commemorations. Qubuka, which means remembering
in English. Now, don't forget to react in the comments and tell us what you think of this video,
and don't forget to subscribe to our YouTube and Instagram.